Finding aid for the Caro Minasian collection of Armenian material Կարօ Մինասեան հայկական հավաքածու LSC.1632
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Photographs: Նկարներ, 1895-1967; Series 13.
  - 13.4 Caro Minasean: Կարօ Մինասեան, 1914-1952
    - Dr. Caro Minasean and Sheikh Abdul Hamid: Դր. Կարօ Մինասեան եւ Շայխ Աբդուլ Համիդ (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Dr. Minasean school photo, Isfahan: Դր. Մինասեանի դպրոցական նկարը Սպահանում, 1914 (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - New Julfa Armenian Central School photo: Նոր Ջուղայի Հայկական Կենտրոնական դպրոցի նկար, 1914-1915 (Box 44, Folder 12)
    - Hospital in Isfahan: Սպահանի հիւանդանոցը, 1935-1937 (Box 44, Folder 13)
      Includes one letter
    - Dr. Caro Minaean's Father's Funeral: Դր. Կարո Մինասեանի հորթաղումը, 1950 (Box 44, Folder 14)
    - Family gravesite: Ընտանեկան գերեզման (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - Album: Ալբոմ (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Personal photographs: Անձնական լուսանկարներ (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Caro Minasean and family: Դր. Կարօ Մինասեան եւ իր ընտանիքը (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - 13.5 East Asia Armenian Community: Արէւելեան Ասիայի հայկական գաղութը, 1895-1900
    This subseries contains photographs from Armenians in East Asia. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Արեւելեան Ասիայի հայերի լուսանկարներ ը:
    - Armenian schools in India: Հայկական դպրոցները Հնդկաստանում, 1895-1900 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Aratoon & Co. Staff: Արաթուն եւ Գործակալներ (Box 44, Folder 16)
      Rangoon, Burma
    - Armenian community of India: Հնդկաստանի հայկական գաղութը (Box 44, Folder 17)
    - Indonesia: Ինդոնեզիա, 1900-1904 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Malaysia: Մալիզիայ (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Singapore: Սինգափուր (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - South East Asia: Հարաւ Արեւելեան Ասիա (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - 13.6 Microfilm: Մանրաժապաւէն, 17th century-18 century
    This subseries contains microfilms of Armenian manuscripts. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է հայ ձեռագիրների մանրաժապաւէն ներ:
    - Armenian old print: Հայկական հին տպագրութիւն, 17th century-18th century (Box 45, Folder 5)
      Prints were in Dr. Minasean's Library but were sent to Erevan, Armenia in 20.5.67; films are in small cylinder small cases
    - Armenian old print: Հայկական հին տպագրութիւն, 1600s-1700s (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - 13.7 Glass Plate Negatives: Ապակեայ սալիկներ, ca.1475-1896
    This subseries contains glass plate negatives and photographs of Armenian and Persian documents and manuscripts. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է հայկական եւ պարսկական փաստաթղթերի եւ ձեռագիրների ապակեայ սալիկներ եւ լուսանկարներ:
    - Sadri's ghabaleh: Սադրիի ղաբալան: صدری قباله: Safavid King's letter, Shah Abbas II: Շահ Աբբաս Բ., Սաֆաւիդ թագաւորի նամակը: نامهء شاه عباس دوم (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Julfa Armenian trade, Captain Nicolas document in margin: Ջուղայի Հայկական առեւտուր, Սպա Նիկոլասի փաստաթուղթ լուսանցքում, 1958 (Box 45, Folder 11)
      Negatives by Hovan 12.X.50; includes 2 b&w photoghraphs of the glass slide
    - Tēr Step'anos Agheksanean: Տէր Ստէփանոս Աղեքսանեան (Box 45, Folder 12)
      Photographed from a manuscript painting.
    - Bzhishk Petros K'alant'arean: Բժիշկ Պետրոս Քալանթարեան (Box 45, Folder 13)
    - Khachatoor Hovaness: Խաչատուր Յովհաննէս, 1817 (Box 45, Folder 14)
      Photographed from a book.
    - Mir Dawoud Zadoor Melik Shah (Ambassador of Persia to France?): Միր Դաւուդ Զադուր Մլիք Շահ (Պարսկաստանի հիւպատոսը Ֆռանսիայում): میر داود زادور ملیک شاه (Box 45, Folder 15)
    - Armenian colophon, referring to the death of Shah Sultan Hossain: Յիշատակարան, Շահ Սուլթան Հօսսայնի մահւան մասին, 1950 (Box 45, Folder 16)
    - Bible parchment illustrated: Աւետարան, նկարազարդ մատեան (Box 45, Folder 7)
      2 glass slides of 1st and 2nd folios
    - Kondak Bnagir: Բնագիր կոնդակ, ca. 1475 AD (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Gladstone letter to Petrues, reference to Cyprus: Գլադսթոնի նամակը Պետրոսին, նշւում է Կիպռոսի մասին, 1896 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - 13.8 Portraits: Դիմանկարներ, 1895-1949
    This subseries contains mostly portraits primarily of ecclesiastical figures. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մեծ մասամբ դիմանկարներ յատկապէս եկեղեցականնե րի:
    - Individual portraits of Armenian ecclesiastical, military & other figures: Անձնական դիմանկարներ հայ եկեղեցականների, զինուորականների եւ այլ անձանց (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Portrait of Ter Hovsep Ter Gevorgean Eliasean: Տէր Յովսէփ Տէր Գեւորգեան Էլիասեան, 1895 (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Georg VI Armenian Catholicos: Գեւորգ Դ. Հայոց Կաթողիկոս, 1949 (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Album of mostly portraits: Անձնական դիմանկարներ (ալբոմ) (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Archives of Mesrovb Dawtean: Մեսրովբ Դաւթեանի արխիվը (Box 46, Folder 2)
      Portraits of Ecclesiastical figures and others from the archives of Mesrovb Dawtean
    - Dpir Mkrtich' Erkarakets'ean: Դպիր Մկրտիչ Երկարակեցեան (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Ecclesiastical photo album: Եկեղեցական նկարներ ալբոմ (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Individuals & portraits: Անձնաւորութիւններ եւ դիմանկարներ (Box 46, Folder 5)
    - Portraits of Armenian Ecclesiastical Figures: դիմանկարներ հայ եկեղեցականների (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Album of portraits: դիմանկարների ալբոմ (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - 13.9 Isfahan: Սպահան, 1963
    This subseries contains photographs of buildings, scenes, and people from Isfahan. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Սպահանի շէնքերի, տեսարանների, եւ մարդոց լուսանկարներ:
    - St. Stephen's Church, Isfahan: Ս. Ստեփան Եկեղեցի, Սպահան (Box 43, Folder 10)
    - Staff of Imperial bank of Persia, Isfahan: Պարսկաստանի Կայսերական Բանկի աշխատակիցներ, Սպահան (Box 43, Folder 11)
    - Imperial Bank of Persia: Պարսկաստանի Կայսերական Բանկ (Box 46, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Isfahan: Նկարներ Սպահանից (Box 46, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Isfahan's Bazar: Նկարներ Սպահանի շուկայից, 1963 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Isfahan and the surrounding areas (album): Նկարներ Սպահանից եւ արուարձաններից, ալբոմ, 1963 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - 13.10 Miscellaneous photographs: Զանազան լուսանկարներ, 1922-1967
    This subseries contains photographs on a wide variety of topics including landscapes, family and religious photographs. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան նիւթերի լուսանկարներ, ներառեալ տեսարաններ, ընտանեկան, եւ կրօնական:
    - Personnel photo: անձնակազմի նկարներ (Box 43, Folder 12)
    - Medical students and staff: Բժշկական ուսանողներ,անձնակազմի (Box 43, Folder 13)
    - Family photograph: Ընտանեկան լուսանկար, 1922 (Box 43, Folder 14)
    - Photographs of religious artifacts and paintings: Կրօնական առարկաների եւ նկարների լուսանկարներ (Box 47, Folder 3)
      These photographs were originally housed in a wooden box, which may now be found in box 56 of this collection.
    - Landscape and Scenery: Տեսարաններ (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Russian photographs: Ռուսական լուսանկարներ (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Family photographs: Ընտանեկան լուսանկարներ (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - Execution scene: Մահապատժի տեսարան, 1967 (Box 56, Folder 2)
      Obtained from Mr. Asad Agodi, Grandson of Mir-Panj (at the left corner with a mace in hand), who carried out the executions
  - 13.11 Persian history and social life: Պարսկաստանի պատմութիւն եւ կեանք
    This subseries contains photographs of mostly members of the ruling class of Persia. Այս ենթակարգը մեծ մասամբ պարունակում է պարսկական իշխող կարգի անդամներու լուսանկարներ:
    - English Embassy personnel, Tehran: Անգլիայի Հիւպատոսարանի անձնակազմը Թեհրանում (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Military Expedition: Զօրարշաւ (Box 43, Folder 16)
    - Zilleh Sultan: Զիլլէհ Սուլթան: ضیل سلطان (Box 43, Folder 17)
      Zilleh Sultan was the governer of Isfahan.
    - Abedin Khan & his son: Աբեդին խան եւ զաւակը: آبدین خان (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Sheikh Khazal in full Mason's dress: Շայխ Խազալը Մասոնական զգեստով :در لباس میسون شیح خزل (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - Bakhtiaries: Բախտիարիները: بختیاریها (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Fatali Shah: Ֆաթալի Շահ: فتح عل? شاه قاجار? (Box 48, Folder 3)
      This includes a picture of a Persian King in a group.
    - Photographs of Persian and Armenian miniature paintings and manuscripts: Պարսկական եւ հայկական մանրանկարչութիւններու լուսանկարներ (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - Persian history: Պարսկաստանի պատմութիւն (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Persian Revolution: Պարսկական յեղափոխութիւն (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - Persian social life: Պարսկական հասարակական կեանք (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - Reza Shah: Ռիզա Շահ: زضا شاه (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - Sheikh Abdul Hamid al'Khazal: Շայխ Աբդուլ Համիդ ալ-Խազալ: شیخ عبدل حمید الخزل (Box 48, Folder 9)
- Mixed items: Խառը առարկաներ եւթղթեր, 1656-1963; Series 14.
  This series contains a wide variety of items, including documents, calendars, the personal items and papers of various individuals, literature, newspaper, and manuscript-related materials, medicinal and post-related materials, obituaries, paintings, and drawings. Of note are the property deeds and transactions, some of which are very old, the catalog of Caro Minasians library, and the literary works and translations into Armenia, including Byrons Parsinia. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, English, French, Hebrew, Arabic, Hindi, and Cyrillic.
  Այս կարգը պարունակում է զանանզան նիւթեր, ներառեալ փաստաթղթեր, օրացոյցեր, զանազան անձերի անձնական նիւթեր եւթուղթեր, գրականութեան,թերթի, եւ ձեռագրերի վերաբերեալ նիւթեր, բժշկական եւ փոսթի վերաբերեալ նիւթեր, մահագոյժեր, նկարչութիւններ, եւ գծագրութիւններ: Նշանակալից են սեփականութեան փաստաթղթերը եւ գործառնութիւնները, Կարօ Մինասեանի գրադարանանին ցուցակը, եւ գրական գործեր եւթարգմանութիւններ, ներառեալ Բայրընի Պարսինիա: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, ֆրանսերէնով, եբրայերէնով, արաբերէնով, հնդկերէնով, եւ կիրիլիցայով են:
  - 14.1 Business: Առեւտուր, 1934
    This subseries contains a few business related contracts. The contracts are in Persian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մի քանի առեւտրին վերաբերող պայմանագրեր: Պայմանագրերը պարսկերէնով են:
    - Contracts: Պայմանագրեր, 1934 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - 14.2 Calendars: Օրացոյցեր, 1893; 1949
    This subseries contains two ecclesiastical calendars. The calendars are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է երկու եկեղեցական օրացոյցներ: Օրացոյցները հայերէնով են:
    - Calendar, Jerusalem: Օրացոյց, Երուսաղէմ, 1893 (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Calendar (handwritten), Charmahal: Օրացոյց (ձեռագրուած), Չհարմահալ, 1949 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - 14.3 Caro Minasian: Կարօ Մինասեան, 1912-1948
    This subseries contains a few materials belonging to Caro Minasian. Of note is the catalog of his library. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Կարօ Մինասեանին պատկանող մի քանի նիւթեր: Նշանակալից է իր գրադարանանին ցուցակը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Lists of books and receipts: Գրքերի ցուցակներ եւ ստացագրեր, 1912-1947 (Box 33, Folder 12)
    - Materials related to Repton School: Ռէպտոն դպրոցի վերաբերող նիւթեր, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 13)
    - Book fragments: Գրքերի հատուածներ, No dates (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - Catalog of Caro Minasian's Library: Կարօ Մինասեանի գրադարանանին ցուցակը, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - 14.4 Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1863-1933
    This subseries contains a variety of documents, including some relating to the Armenian General Benevolent Union and the Russian Imperial Council in Persia. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, and French. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան փաստաթղթեր, ներառեալ մի քանի Հայկական Ընդհանուր Բարեգործական Միւթեան վերաբերերեալ եւ Ռուսական կայսերական խորհուրդի վերաբերեալ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ ֆրանսերէնով են:
    - George Mackertich's passport and travel documents: Գեւորգ Մկրտիչեանի անձնագիրը եւ ճամբորդական փաստաթղթեր, 1941 (Box 28, Folder 27)
    - Documents relating to the Russian Imperial Council in Persia: Պարսկաստանում Ռուսաստանի կայսերական խորհուրդի վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր, 1863-1865 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Document on Agha Seth and his travels: Աղա Սէթի եւ իր ճամբորդութեան մասին Փաստաթուղթ, 1866 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      Translated from Persian to Armenian (1283 Hijri)
    - Documents relating to the Armenian General Benevolent Union: Հայկական Բարեգործական Ընդհանուր Միութեան վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր, 1933 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - 14.5 Harut'iwn Tēr Hovhan: Յարութիւն Տէր Յովհան, 1845-1852
    This subseries contains a book of accounts, inventory, and the will of Harutiwn Tēr Hovhan. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Յարութիւն Տէր Հովհանի պատկանող մի հաշուէտումար, մի համար եւ կտակը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Book of Accounts (Martiros Harut'iwn Tēr Hovhanean): Հաշուէտումար Մարտիրոսի Յարութիւն Տէր Յովհանեան, 1845-1852 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Will of Harut'iwn Tēr Hovan: Կտակ Յարութիւն Տէր Յովհանեանի, 1849 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Inventory of Harut'iwn Tēr Hovan: Համար Յարութիւն Տէր Յովհանեանի, 1852 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - 14.6 Hayastani Koch'nak: Հայաստանի Կոչնակ, 1926
    This subseries contains one document relating to the Armenian newspaper "Hayastani Kochnak." The document is in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հայաստանի Կոչնակի պատկանող մի փաստաթուղթ: Փաստաթուղթը հայերէնով է:
    - Document relating to "Hayastani Koch'nak" (newspaper): Հայաստանի Կոչնակին վերաբերող փաստաթուղթ, 1926 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - 14.7 Literature: Գրականութիւն, 1778-1950
    This subseries contains various literary works, including poetry of Emil Minasian, a work entitled "Journey to India," by Avetik' Tsaghikeants', and poetry translated into Armenian including Byrons Parsinia. Materials are in Armenian and Persian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան գրական գործեր, ներառեալ Էմիլ Մինասեանի բանաստեղծութ իւններ, մի գործ անուանեալ Ճանապարհորդո ւթիւն ի Հնդկաստան, եւ հայերէնիթարգ մանուած բանաստեղծութ իւններ ներառեալ Բայրընի Պարսինիա: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ պարսկերէնով են:
    - Book of poems from various authors, translated to Armenian and Translation of Bayron's Parisina: Ոտանաւորների գիրք տարբեր գրողներից հայերէնթարգմանութիւններ եւ Բայրընի Պարիսինա (հայերէնիթարգմանուած), 1927 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Emil Minasean poetry (clippings from newspapers): Էմիլ Մինասեանի բանաստեղծութիւններ (թերթերի հատուածներ), 1948 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Persian poetry and portrait of famous Armenian poet Gegham Saryan: Պարսկերէն բանաստեղծութիւն եւ յայտնի հայ գրող Գեղամ Սարեանի լուսանկար, No dates (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Poetry and a booklist belonging to Tēr Mesrovb Davitean: Տէր Մեսրովբ Դավիթեանի բանաստեղծութիւն եւ գրքերի ցուցակ, 1778-1908;1950 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Journey to India, Avetik' Tsaghikeants': Ճանապարհորդութիւն ի Հնդկաստան, Աւետիք Ծաղիկեանց, 1832 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - 14.8 Manuscripts and Early Printed Books: Մատեաններ, No dates
    This subseries contains photographs and samples of pages from manuscript and early printed books, as well as ornamental designs for books. Materials are in Armenian, Persian and Cyrillic. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է ձեռագիրների եւ կանխաւ տպագրուած գրքերի լուսանկարներ եւ օրինակներ, նաեւ մատենազարդեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ կիրիլիցայով են:
    - Manuscript pages (Cyrillic): Մատեանների էջեր (Կիրիլիցա), No dates (Box 34, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript ornamental designs: Մատենազարդեր, No dates (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Photographs of manuscripts in Yerevan: Երեւանում մատեաների նկարներ, No dates (Box 34, Folder 15)
    - Photographs of pages relating to the killing of Bishop Eznik: Եզնիկ Աբեղայի սպաննութեան վերաբերող էջերի նկարներ (Box 34, Folder 16)
  - 14.9 Martin Sarkies: Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեան, 1873-1889
    This susbseries contains documents relating to the seafaring life of Martin Sarkies. There are his certificate of competency as a first class engineer, as well as his certificate of discharge. Materials are in English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեանի նաւաստիութեա ն կեանքի վերաբերող վաւերագիրենե ր: Կան իր վաւերագրութի ւն Առաջին կարգի էնժինէրի կոչման եւ իր ազատումի վաւերագիրը: Նիւթերը անգլերէնով են:
    - Certificate of competency as First class Engineer. Martin. Sarkies: Վաւերագրութիւն Առաջին կարգի էնժինէրի կոչման՝ Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեան, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    - Certificate of discharge for Martin Sarkies (seaman): Ազատումի վաւերագիրը՝ Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեան (նաւաստի), 1882-1889 (Box 34, Folder 18)
  - 14.10 Medicine: բժշկութիւն, 1904-1962
    This subseries contains articles, pamphlets, and other documents relating to medicine. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, English, and French. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է բժշկութեան վերաբերող յօդուածներ, բացիկներ, եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ ֆրանսերէնով են:
    - Medical articles: Բժշկական յօդուածներ, 1904-1962 (Box 34, Folder 19)
    - Document relating to Armenian folk medicine: հայ ժողովրդական բժշկութեան վերաբերող փաստաթուղթ, 1873-1935 (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - Medical and pharmaceutical pamphlets: բժշկական եւ դեղաբուժական բացիկներ, No dates (Box 34, Folder 21)
  - 14.11 Miscellaneous materials: Զանազան նիւթեր, 1656-1957
    This subseries contains a number of different items. Of note is the Hebrew votive painting, the receipt of Moliere, and the birth cloth. Materials are in Armenian, English, French, and Hebrew. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան նիւթեր: Նշանակալից են եբրայերէն կրօնական նկարչութիւնը, Մոլիէռի ստացագիրը, եւ ծննդաբերական լաթը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, ֆրանսերէնով, եւ եբրայերէնով են:
    - Armenian alphabet print on cloth and a poster commemorating the 100th anniversary of Armenian journalism: Կտաւէ հայ այբուբենը եւ մի ազդ հայ լրագրութեան հարիւրամսեակի առիթով, ca. 1890s (Box 28, Folder 25)
    - Decorative painting and Hebrew votive painting: Զարդանկարչութիւն եւ Եբրայերէն կրօնական նկարչութիւն (Box 28, Folder 28)
    - Receipt of Moliere and article about the author: Մոլիէռի ստացագիր եւ իր մասին յօդուած, 1656-1957 (Box 34, Folder 22)
    - Book fragments, newspaper clippings, documents, and correspondence: Գրքի եւթերթի հատուածներ, փաստաթղթեր, եւ նամակներ, 1846-1946 (Box 34, Folder 23)
    - Wedding songs: Հարսանեկան երգեր, 1849 (Box 34, Folder 24)
    - Birth cloth or yamshaq: Ծննդաբերական լաթ կամ Եամշաղ (Box 34, Folder 25)
    - Martyros Joakim's handwritten booklets: Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանի ձեռագրուած գրքոյկներ, 1873 (Box 34, Folder 26)
    - Wooden storage box: Փայտէ տուփ (Box 56, Folder 1)
      This box included several rolled photographs that may now be found in box 47, folders 3-4.
    - Cloth pouch: Կտաւէ տոպրակ (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - 14.12 Obituary: Մահագոյժ, 1917-1926
    This subseries contains a eulogy and an obituary. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մի մահագոյժ եւ մի գովասանութիւ ն: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Eulogy for Shukurean: Գովասանութիւն Շուքուրեանի համար, 1917 (Box 34, Folder 27)
    - Gēorg Zōrabean's Obituary: Գէորգ Զօրաբեանի մահագոյժ, 1926 (Box 34, Folder 28)
  - 14.13 Paintings and Drawings: Նկարչութիւններ եւ գծագրութիւններ, 1832-1854
    This subseries contains a number of different paintings and drawings. Most are portraits of various personages. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է զանազան նկարչութիւնն եր եւ գծագրութիւնն եր, մեծ մասամբ անձերի դիմանկարներ:
    - Drawing of sword of Levon of Kilikia and other famous personages: Լեւոնի սուրի եւ այլ յայտնի անձերի գծագրութիւններ, 1875 (Box 28, Folder 26)
    - Portrait of Harut'iwn Kirakosean: Յարութիւն Կիրակոսի դիմանկար, 1832 (Box 34, Folder 29)
    - Portrait of Mkrtich' Zōrabean: Մկրտիչ Զօրաբեանի դիմանկար, 1854 (Box 34, Folder 30)
    - Painting (print) from Karo Davitean by Simon Samson's daughter's son: Տպագիր նկար Կարո Դավիթեանից, Սիմոն Սամսոնի աղջկայ տղան, No dates (Box 34, Folder 31)
    - Persian paintings and drawings: Պարսկական նկարչութիւններ եւ գծագրութիւններ (Box 34, Folder 32)
  - 14.14 Post related materials: Փոստին վերաբերեալ նիւթեր, 1846-1952
    This subseries contains envelopes, stamps, and postal receipts in Armenian, Persian, Arabic, Hindi, and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է ծրարներ, նամականիշներ, եւ փոստի ստացագրեր հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, արաբերէնով, հնդկերէնով եւ անգլերէնով:
    - Correspondence envelopes of Johannes Mackertoom: Յովհաննէս Մկրտումեանի նամակածրարներ, 1846-1867 (Box 34, Folder 33)
    - Postal receipts of Johannes Mackertoom: Յովհաննէս Մկրտումեանի փօստի ստացագրեր, 1853-1860 (Box 34, Folder 34)
    - Receipts of George Mackertich: Գէորգ Մկրտիչեանի ստացագրեր, 1910-1952 (Box 34, Folder 35)
    - Envelopes with stamps: Ծրարներ նամականիշներով, No dates (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - 14.15 Property deeds and transactions: Սեփականութեան փաստաթղթեր եւ գործառնութիւններ, 1734-1848?
    This subseries contains property deeds and transactions in Armenian. Some of the materials are notable for their antiquity. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է փաստաթղթեր եւ գործառնութիւ ններ հայերէնով: Շատերը նշանակալից են իրենց հնութեան արումով:
    - Property transactions: Կալուածների վերաբերեալ փաստաթղթեր, 1734-1844 (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - The deed of the house that Mr. Amirkhan has purchased: Պրն. Ամիրխանի գնած նունի փաստաթուղթը, 1848 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Property dispute involving Npastamatuyts' handznakhumb and Murad Mirza: Ունեցւածքի պատկանելութեան վերաբերեալ անհամաձայնութիւն Նպաստամատոյց Յանձնախմբի եւ Մուրադ Միրզայի միչեւ, 1823 (Box 35, Folder 3)
- Books: Գրքեր, 1756-1963; Series 15.
  This vast series contains mostly handwritten (many unpublished) books as well as published books and handwritten copies of published books. The books cover a wide range of topics including scientific, mathematical, and medicinal, religious, ethnographical, poetry, folk tales, and other literature, as well as dictionaries and textbooks. Notable is the typewritten copy of Sukeaseans New Julfan dictionary, a Armenian-Indonesian dictionary, ethnographical works on Charmahal, and the many collections of folk tales, songs, and poetry. Materials are predominantly in Armenian, with some English, Persian, French, and Russian.
  Այս մեծածաւալ կարգը պարունակում է մեծ մասամբ ձեռագրուած (շատերը չհրատարակուած) գրքեր նաեւ հրատարակուած գրքեր եւ հրատարակուած գրքերի ձեռագրուած օրինակներ: Գրքերը շատ նիւթերին են վերաբերում, ներառեալ գիտական,թուաբանական, բժշկական, ազգագրական, բանաստեղծական, ժողովրդական պատմուածքներ եւ այլ գրականութիւն, նաեւ բառարաններ եւ դասագրքեր: Նշանակալից են մեքենագրուած Սուքեասեանի Նոր-Ջուղայի բարբառի բառարանը, հայերէնից ինդոնէզերէն բառարանը, Չարմահալի մասին ազգագրական երկեր, եւ շատ ժողովրդական պատմուածքների, երգերի, եւ բանաստեղծութեան հաւաքածոներ: Նիւթերը մեծ մասամբ հայերէնով են, մի քիչ անգլերէնով, պարսկերէնով, ֆրանսերէնով, եւ ռուսերէնով:
  - Martyros Ter Joakim: Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեան, 1836-1872; Subseries 15.1.
    This subseries contains books belonging to Martyros Ter Joakim. The books are all handwritten, and some are copied from published books. Of note is the English-Armenian dictionary and phrasebook. The books are in Armenian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանին պատկանող գրքեր: Բոլոր գրքերը ձեռագրուած են, մի քանի հրատարակուած գրքերից օրինակուած: Նշանակալից է Անգլերէն- Հայերէն բառարան եւ արտահայտութե ան գիրք: Գրքերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - English-Armenian dictionary and phrase book: Անգլերէն- Հայերէն բառարան եւ արտահայտութեան գիրք, 19th century (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Sermon on the Birth of Jesus Christ: Քարոզ յաղագս ծննդեանն Յ[իսու]սի Ք[րիստո]սի, 19th century (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous books: Զանազան գրքեր (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - order of Holy Mass according to the Ritual of the Holy Roman Church: Կանոն Սրբոյ Պատարագի ըստ ծիսի Հռովմէական Սուրբ Եկեղեցւոյ, 1836 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - Teaching of the Christian Faith, according to the Orthodox Tradition of the Armenian Church: Հրահանգ քրիստոնեական հաւատոյ, ըստ Ուղղափառ դաւանութեան Եկեղեցւոյ Հայաստանեաց, 1850 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - Liturgical Book: Ծիսական գիրք, 1868 (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - Letter Book of Eliazar Ter Johannes: Էլիազար Տէր Յովհաննէսի նամակագիրք, 1871 (Box 48, Folder 17)
    - History of the Holy Scriptures: Պատմութիւն Սուրբ Գրոց, 1872 (Box 48, Folder 18)
  - George Mackertich: Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան, 1900-1932; Subseries 15.2.